As usual the children put on a play at the end of term.
孩子们照例在期末上演话剧
John wrote this year's play.
约翰写今年的话剧
Here it is.
是这样的
The bird
鸟
Scene one: A market stall
第一幕   一个街市档位
Birds for sale. Birds for sale. They all sing beautifully.
卖鸟了   卖鸟了   它们都唱得很动听
How much is that bird?
那只鸟多少钱
This yellow one?
这只黄色的吗
Yes.
是的
Thirty dollars.
三十美元
And the cage?
笼子呢
Fifty dollars. You can have the bird and the cage for sixty-five dollars.
五十美元   鸟和笼子一共六十五美元卖你
Does the bird sing?
鸟唱歌吗
Of course it does.
当然了
Here you are. Here's sixty-five dollars.
给你   这是六十五美元
Scene two: Inside the old man's flat
第二幕   在老人的公寓里
What have you got there?
你拿的是什么啊
A bird. I bought it in the market.
一只鸟   我在市场买的
We haven't got enough money for a bird.
我们没钱养鸟
We need lots of things but we don't need a bird.
我们需要很多东西   但我们不需要一只鸟
I can take it for a walk in its cage every day.
我可以每天提着笼子带它去散步
It'll sing to me.
它会对我唱歌
You're a silly old man. You waste our money.
你真是个傻老头   你浪费了我们的钱
Don't you like listening to a bird sing?
你难道不喜欢听鸟唱歌吗
I like eating a bird more! Why didn't you buy a chicken or a duck?
我更喜欢吃鸟   你为什么不买只鸡或鸭呢
Because they don't sing.
因为它们不唱歌
Scene three: Inside the flat- two weeks later
第三幕   在公寓里   两周后
That bird hasn't sung yet.
那只鸟还没唱歌呢
I know. And I've taken it for a walk every day.
我知道   而且我已经每天带它去散步了
Is there anything wrong with it?
它有什么问题吗
I don't know.
我不知道
What a waste of money! Sixty-five dollars for that bird and it won't sing.
多浪费钱啊   六十五美元买那只鸟   还不会唱歌
I'll take it for one more walk.
我再带它去散个步
Scene four: On the street
第四幕   在街上
Good morning, sir.
早上好   先生
Good morning.
早上好
You've got a fine bird in that cage.
你笼子里的鸟真漂亮
Yes, but it won't sing.
是的   但它不唱歌
It won't sing! I can make it sing.
它不会唱歌   我可以让它唱歌
How?
如何
Put it down, sir, next to my bowl.
把它放下   先生   放在我的碗边上
The beggar whistles to the bird and it begins to sing.
乞丐对鸟吹口哨   它开始唱歌
I can't whistle like that.
我不能像那样吹口哨
The bird will never sing for me.
鸟不会为我歌唱了
Then why not give it to me, sir?
那为什么不把它给我呢   先生
It will sing for me every day.
它会每天为我歌唱
You can come and listen to it.
你可以过来听
That's a very good idea.
那是个非常好的主意
Scene five: Inside the flat
第五幕   在公寓里
Where's the bird?
鸟在哪儿
I gave it to the beggar on the corner of the street.
我把它给了街角的那个乞丐
You gave it to the beggar! Why did you do that?
你把它给了那个乞丐   你为什么这样做
Because it'll sing for him.
因为它会为他歌唱
You gave that beggar sixty-five dollars!
你给了那个乞丐六十五美元
You don't understand. The bird won't sing for me but it will sing for him.
你不懂   鸟不会为我歌唱   但它会为他歌唱
I can listen to it every day now.
现在我可以每天听了
But it's not your bird now. It's his.
但它现在不是你的鸟了啊   是他的了
Yes, but it's not his song.
是的   但这不是他的歌
I wanted the song, not the bird. Now I've got it.
我想要的是歌   不是鸟   现在我得到了
You're a very silly old man.
你是个非常傻的老头
Am I?
是吗